<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Duck River Biodiversity</title><link>https://tmesaglio.github.io/duck-river-biodiversity-survey/en/</link><description>Recent content on Duck River Biodiversity</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://tmesaglio.github.io/duck-river-biodiversity-survey/en/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Background</title><link>https://tmesaglio.github.io/duck-river-biodiversity-survey/en/background/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://tmesaglio.github.io/duck-river-biodiversity-survey/en/background/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In 2020, I was looking for new green spaces to explore in western Sydney. In late April, I stumbled upon Wategora Reserve for the first time, having never visited it (or even known of its existence) beforehand. I visited a second time in early May, but then largely forgot about the reserve. In early September, however, I was starting to go a little bit crazy being stuck inside all the time during COVID lockdowns, and decided to visit Wategora again now that it was spring. After reading an information sign in the reserve, I became aware of the &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Price List&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Maps and site information</title><link>https://tmesaglio.github.io/duck-river-biodiversity-survey/en/maps/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://tmesaglio.github.io/duck-river-biodiversity-survey/en/maps/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Stretching ~1.3 km from north to south, and ~350 m at its widest point, my survey area covered ~25 ha (0.25 km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;) across Wategora Reserve and, immediately south of it, the riverine vegetation adjacent to Everley Park. Located in western Sydney, New South Wales, the survey area spans the suburbs of Chester Hill, South Granville and Auburn, and is under the jurisdiction of Cumberland Council. It is in a highly urbanised area, and is surrounded by sporting fields, a golf course, and industrial estates and commercial properties.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Methods</title><link>https://tmesaglio.github.io/duck-river-biodiversity-survey/en/methods/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://tmesaglio.github.io/duck-river-biodiversity-survey/en/methods/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Because my survey was designed to be comprehensive, I did not run any quadrats, transects, etc., but rather continuously surveyed the entire reserve ad nauseum. Most of the species I recorded were observed through simple active searching, but I also set up a UV lamp and moth sheet during many of my night surveys to survey insects. I endeavoured to survey as non-destructively as possible, but I did collect some insect specimens to send to experts for identification. I also collected a number of plant specimens and deposited them at the NSW Herbarium, some for identification and others for their value as vouchers.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Threats</title><link>https://tmesaglio.github.io/duck-river-biodiversity-survey/en/threats/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://tmesaglio.github.io/duck-river-biodiversity-survey/en/threats/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I will keep this section brief, as it is comprehensively treated within my final report itself, but the survey area is threatened by a myriad of processes and entities, including (but not limited to) invasion by non-native species, erosion, weather extremes, pollution, and inadequate management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Undoubtedly, the most significant current threat to the reserve&amp;rsquo;s biodiversity is the proliferation and spread of non-native plants. During my survey I observed 311 non-native plant species, exceeding the number of natives (287). Although many of these non-natives are having little to no impact in the survey area, e.g., singular occurrences of garden escapees such as &lt;em&gt;Dimorphotheca ecklonia&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Dracaena draco&lt;/em&gt;, a great number of non-native plant species are negatively impacting the survey area&amp;rsquo;s biodiversity right now, with impacts including altered water flow, spread of disease, creation of excess shade, smothering of native trees and shrubs, and outcompetition/displacement of native species.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Notable plant species</title><link>https://tmesaglio.github.io/duck-river-biodiversity-survey/en/important/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://tmesaglio.github.io/duck-river-biodiversity-survey/en/important/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Whilst there are many plant species that are significant or locally rare within the survey area, represented by just one or a small handful of individuals, a lot of these are more common/widely distributed across Sydney or NSW. However, as listed by James, McDougall and Benson in their 1999 &lt;a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/331586736_Rare_Bushland_Plants_of_Western_Sydney_Second_edition_1999"&gt;Rare Bushland Plants of Western Sydney (2nd edition)&lt;/a&gt;, there are five regionally significant plants considered rare in Western Sydney that I&amp;rsquo;ve observed in the reserve.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Species discovery</title><link>https://tmesaglio.github.io/duck-river-biodiversity-survey/en/silverfish/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://tmesaglio.github.io/duck-river-biodiversity-survey/en/silverfish/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;During my survey I observed a number of undescribed species, including a native mushroom (&lt;em&gt;Agaricus&lt;/em&gt; sp.), multiple invertebrates (e.g., grasshoppers, spiders), and two phrase name plant species, &lt;em&gt;Arthropodium&lt;/em&gt; sp. South-east Highlands (N.G.Walsh 811) Vic. Herbarium and &lt;em&gt;Alternanthera&lt;/em&gt; sp. A Flora of New South Wales (M.Gray 5187) J.Palmer. One of these cases, however, was particularly notable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In late March 2021, I found a single silverfish under a fallen &lt;em&gt;Melaleuca decora&lt;/em&gt; bark sheet at the southwestern corner of the southern exotic grassland. It was quite active, running among bark and stick litter, and likely only came to the surface after the heavy rains and flooding in mid to late March 2021. After a family identification from entomologist Nikola Szucsich on iNaturalist, I sent my photos to researcher/expert Graeme Smith, and he noted:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Results</title><link>https://tmesaglio.github.io/duck-river-biodiversity-survey/en/results/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://tmesaglio.github.io/duck-river-biodiversity-survey/en/results/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Across 378.6 hours of surveying, I recorded 1931 species. I provide an exhaustive annotated and illustrated checklist for every one of these species in my final report itself, but in summary:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Algae - 2 species.&lt;/strong&gt; Both green algae: &lt;em&gt;Cladophora glomerata&lt;/em&gt;, submerged in the creek, and &lt;em&gt;Basicladia ramulosa&lt;/em&gt; growing as an epibiont on the carapace of an Eastern Long-necked Turtle (&lt;em&gt;Chelodina longicollis&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bryophytes - 24 species.&lt;/strong&gt; One hornwort (&lt;em&gt;Phaeoceros carolinianus&lt;/em&gt;), 11 liverworts and 12 mosses. Includes 2 non-native species: the liverwort &lt;em&gt;Lunularia cruciata&lt;/em&gt; and the moss &lt;em&gt;Leptodictyum riparium&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Future work</title><link>https://tmesaglio.github.io/duck-river-biodiversity-survey/en/future/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://tmesaglio.github.io/duck-river-biodiversity-survey/en/future/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Species discovery has not stopped!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some taxa, I&amp;rsquo;m confident that I&amp;rsquo;ve observed or identified all species currently present within the survey area. For many groups, however, the species I recorded during my survey are probably only scratching the surface. Some of the more obvious of these, and some of the low-hanging fruit, include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nocturnal mammals&lt;br&gt;
Fungi (including lichens)&lt;br&gt;
Bryophytes&lt;br&gt;
Leaf litter invertebrates&lt;br&gt;
Plant taxa such as &lt;em&gt;Lepidosperma&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Plantago&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Vittadinia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Verbena&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Gamochaeta&lt;/em&gt; (for which I&amp;rsquo;m reasonably sure I&amp;rsquo;m currently overlooking cryptic diversity in the survey area) &lt;br&gt;
Aquatic taxa &lt;br&gt;
Grasses &lt;br&gt;
Galls and leaf miners&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>About the author</title><link>https://tmesaglio.github.io/duck-river-biodiversity-survey/en/author/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://tmesaglio.github.io/duck-river-biodiversity-survey/en/author/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;My name&amp;rsquo;s Thomas Mesaglio and I&amp;rsquo;m a PhD candidate at the University of New South Wales Sydney; my thesis focuses on quantifying our knowledge of Australian plant biodiversity, and developing identification tools, survey and species description protocols, and general data frameworks for improving this knowledge. Although most of my research over the past few years has focused on analyses of citizen science data, I&amp;rsquo;ve published scientific papers across a wide range of disciplines, including marine forensics, bushfire recovery and invertebrate ecology and taxonomy. You can view my papers and other academic works at &lt;a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1096-6066"&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Version history</title><link>https://tmesaglio.github.io/duck-river-biodiversity-survey/en/version-history/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://tmesaglio.github.io/duck-river-biodiversity-survey/en/version-history/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Version 1.0 - released 5 December 2022&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Summary:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Initial release&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Version 1.1 - released 17 December 2022&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Summary:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New section added&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 new species added/identified from existing observations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Refined identification for 2 species&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coarsened identification for 2 species (both still maintained as unique morphospecies)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Description updated for 1 species&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Photographic voucher updated for 1 species&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Correction of 1 factual error&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Updated non-native plant species count&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Updated number of iNaturalist identifiers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Total species count updated to 1928.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Version 1.2 - released 12 January 2023&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>